Alright, the next section deals with the colon.
The first disorder that we want to talk about
is Hirschsprung's disease.
In this disorder, you have defective relaxation
and peristalsis of the rectum
and the distal sigmoid colon.
There's an association of Hirschsprung's disease
with Down syndrome.
That's a particularly high yield thing to be aware of.
Now, the disorder arises because there's a congenital
failure of the ganglion cells to descend.
Let me remind you that the ganglion cells
are derived from the neural crest
and that they descend into the wall of the bowel
and when they're present in the wall of the bowel
they have particular function.
But before you can understand that
and how it relates to the disease,
you've got to understand normal.
So let's go back and remind ourselves
that the bowel wall is comprised of mucosa,
a submucosa, a muscularis propria, and a serosa.
And then remember that the muscularis propria
has an inner circular layer
and an outer longitudinal layer.
Now, present within the wall of this bowel
is also ganglion cells
and you've got two groups of ganglion cells.
You've got one set here
which is called Auerbach's myenteric plexus.
This is present between the layers of the lamina propria
and most important is that it's important for
motility and relaxation.
So you need these ganglion cells to have good peristalsis
and also to be able to relax properly.
So that's the first group of ganglion cells.
The second set of ganglion cells
is actually present in the submucosa.
It's called Meisner's submucosal plexus
and this helps to regulate blood flow, secretions, absorption, etc.
And so you need both of these sets of ganglion cells for proper function.
Now what happens again in Hirschsprung's disease is that in the rectum
and possibly the distal sigmoid colon, but let's focus on the rectum,
you are going to be lacking the ganglion cells of both layers.
And so if the ganglion cells of both layers are lacking,
you're not going to have good peristalsis so you won't be able to pass stool through appropriately
and you won't have good relaxation so you won't be able to relax the rectum appropriately
to get the stool to move forward and eventually out of the body.
And so the clinical features of this disorder are all going to be based on that central theme
which is that there's going to be obstruction.
So the babies would fail to pass meconium, there'd be an empty vault on digital rectal exam,
there'd be dilation of the bowel proximal to the area of obstruction.
So imagine if this is the rectum here and you can't relax it properly and you don't have good peristalsis,
then behind it you're going to get massive dilatation of the bowel that again is proximal to that area.
And there's a risk here, of course, as you get dilation and further dilation, there's a risk of rupture.
The way by which the diagnosis is made in this particular disorder is rectal suction biopsy
and the rectal suction biopsy will show a lack of ganglion cells.
Now it's important to note that you need to do rectal suction biopsy and that's particularly high yield.
And the idea here is that the standard biopsy simply only takes a piece of mucosa,
but if you take a piece of mucosa you won't be able to ask the question of whether the ganglion cells are absent or present
because the mucosa normally does not have ganglion cells to begin with.
So basically what you need to do is you need to actually create a little bit of suction against the rectal wall
so that you actually pull the submucosa into the biopsy.
And by looking at the submucosa you can ask the question, are the ganglion cells present or absent?
Because they should normally be present there and if they're missing then you can truly say that they are absent.
So very important and very high yield to know that you've got to use the rectal suction biopsy
to be able to truly look at the ganglion cells.
The treatment of this disorder is to resect the area of involved bowel, so for example if you're looking at the disease
and this is the rectum, you may have no ganglion cells here and then no ganglion cells here
and then no ganglion cells here, but eventually you'll come to a region where there are ganglion cells.
And so what the surgeon will do is resect this area that does not have ganglion cells
and leave behind the area that does have ganglion cells.
Okay, the next disorder is colonic diverticula. The idea here is that you get a diverticulum or an outpouching
and of course in this particular case it would involve the colon.
The outpouching is a pseudodiverticulum. Remember that the pseudodiverticulum means that you only push out part of the wall instead of the entire wall.
So that's what the pseudo refers to, part as opposed to the entire wall.
And in this particular case it happens to be the mucosa and the submucosa that go through the muscularis propria.
So the idea here is that if you've got your mucosa and then you've got submucosa and then you've got muscularis propria
and of course then you've got serosa, what happens is that you get an outpouching of both the submucosa and the mucosa like this through the muscularis propria.
And then of course this would become normal again.
Now the reason why patients get these is because it's related to wall stress.
Anything that's going to increase wall stress is going to increase the risk of pushing the submucosa and the mucosa through the muscularis propria.
So it's associated with constipation, a low fiber diet, which again both of these would result in straining commonly seen in older adults.
The more tension on the wall over time, the increased risk of developing colonic diverticula.
What's important to note is that it arises where the vasa recta traverse the muscularis propria and that's a weak point in the colon wall.
And the most common location is the sigmoid colon.
The idea here again being that if I were to draw you this image again, so this was the mucosa.
And then again here this is the submucosa.
And then you've got the muscularis propria, which I'm going to draw particularly thick here.
So this is the muscularis propria.
What happens is remember that you've got these veins called the vasa recta and the vasa recta, they traverse the muscularis propria when they come up.
And as they traverse the muscularis propria, they are then going to weaken the wall slightly at that point,
which then creates the opportunity for this diverticulum to form.
Now what's very important is that notice that this diverticulum is right next to this vein and that's going to be very important when I talk about some of the complications in a moment.
Here's a picture of a diverticulum.
It's very similar to what I've drawn except that you're looking at the surface of the colon and this hole represents the diverticulum.
Here's a histologic image highlighting what I've already drawn for you.
Of course you've got your mucosa and your submucosa as I'm writing up here in the upper left hand side of the screen.
And then this is the muscularis propria and you can clearly see that both the mucosa and the submucosa have come through the muscularis propria.
Now of course that would arise in the region where the vein is actually coming up, which again is a weak point in the wall.
Now diverticuli are usually asymptomatic and many patients develop these as they age, but there are some associated complications to be aware of in their high yield.
The first is rectal bleeding. You recall that the diverticulum is right up against the wall of the vein, so it wouldn't be hard for bleeding to occur.
And these patients, when they get bleeding, they get something called hematochesia where they get bright red blood being passed into the toilet, for example.
You can also get diverticulitis. That's easy to understand if this is the diverticulum.
If you were to obstruct this diverticulum with fecal material, that would give you inflammation of the wall eventually, which would be diverticulitis.
And that is going to present with what they call left-sided appendicitis-like symptoms.
So it's sort of like appendicitis, but of course appendicitis would be on the right side, this would be on the left side.
And then another important complication could be a fistula. Remember that a fistula is a connection between two tubes.
So in this particular case, imagine that you've got this diverticulum here. Imagine that the wall gets inflamed, and when the wall gets inflamed, that weakens the wall,
and then the wall subsequently bursts or ruptures, and then it plugs into another tube. For example, in this case, let's make this the bladder.
So the classic type of fistula that you often can see on an examination would be something called a colovesicular fistula,
where you get a diverticulum that is plugged into, for example, the bladder.
Now the way by which this would present is that you would have air or stool in the urine.
The next disorder is angiodysplasia. Angio means blood vessel. Dysplasia means that the blood vessel has become malformed.
So it's an acquired malformation of the mucosal and submucosal vessels.
What is important to note is that it usually arises in the cecum, in the right colon, due to high wall tension.
And this is going to present as hematochesia in an older adult. I'll make this very simple for you.
If you have high stress in the left colon, you're going to get diverticula, and those can present with hematochesia.
If you have high stress in the right side of the colon, you get angiodysplasia, and that can also present as hematochesia.
So that's the way I remember it. High stress on the left and high stress on the right can result in hematochesia,
but the pathogenesis is a little bit different.
Hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia. This is a hereditary disorder in which patients have telangiectasias.
And telangiectasias are dilated, thin-walled blood vessels. Now this is autosomal dominant.
It particularly occurs in the nasopharynx and the GI tract.
And when these rupture, when these telangiectasias rupture, the patient presents with bleeding.
Here's a classic picture of a patient with hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia.
And these little red areas here represent the telangiectatic blood vessels.
Again, anywhere from the oropharynx slash nasopharynx through the GI tract.
So it's a cause of bleeding in the GI tract.
The next disorder is ischemic colitis. This is where you get ischemic damage to the colon.
Usually it occurs at the splenic flexure, and the most common cause is atherosclerosis of the SMA.
Now, if you get atherosclerosis of the SMA, let's pretend that this is the SMA and you've got atherosclerosis,
now you're going to be decreasing the blood flow.
And when you decrease the blood flow, the area that's furthest away,
at the very, very most distal end of that blood supply is where you're going to get signs of ischemia.
And it happens to be that the splenic flexure is the very last thing fed by the SMA.
And so that's where the damage would tend to occur.
Now, the way that this is going to present is with postprandial pain and weight loss.
Now, the idea is that when the patient eats, they increase the energy requirements of the gut.
And so when you increase the energy requirements, that's the time that you're going to notice that the blood supply is not appropriate.
And so they get postprandial pain.
It's sort of like the way that a patient gets angina when they exercise or walk upstairs.
You know, if they've got decreased blood flow going to the heart and then they exercise, then that's when they get the chest pain.
So in the same way, if you've got decreased blood flow going to the colon and then the patient exercises or eats,
because that's the exercising of the colon, they're going to have postprandial pain.
And at the same time, they lose weight because they get this pain and so they don't eat as much.
If there is complete loss or severe loss of the blood supply, that would result in infarction.
And that would again present with bloody diarrhea and pain.
So ischemia would simply give you postprandial pain, whereas a continued lack of oxygen or severe lack of oxygen would give you infarction resulting in bloody diarrhea.
Irritable bowel syndrome is a relapsing abdominal pain with bloating flatulence and a change in bowel habits, so the patients can have diarrhea or constipation.
It improves with defecation.
It's classically seen in middle-aged females.
We don't have any identifiable pathologic changes in this disorder, so that if you did a biopsy, you wouldn't see much.
However, we do know that it's related to a disturbed intestinal motility and that dietary fiber can improve the symptoms.
The last discussion in this section concerns colonic polyps, and this is particularly high yield.
Basically, with colonic polyps, you're dealing with a raised protrusion of the colonic mucosa.
So that if this is the surface of the colon, we get this raised bump of the mucosa, and that's called a colonic polyp.
There are two common types, and then there are some relatively rare types.
We're going to focus on the two common types first.
The most common type of polyp in the colon is a hyperplastic polyp.
This is due to hyperplasia of the glands.
It's the most common type of polyp.
It usually arises in the left colon, and it's benign with no malignant potential, and that's important.
It is benign, and it doesn't have the ability were it to be left in the patient to become anything worse.
Now, what I'd like to remind you of is that were you to look at this polyp on microscopy,
what you would see is that the surface of the polyp has this sort of sawtooth appearance,
and that's called a serrated appearance, and that's the classic finding on microscopy.
The second type of polyp is called an adenomatous polyp.
This is a neoplastic proliferation of glands, again, second most common type.
It is benign but super high yield.
It has the ability were it to be left in a patient to become cancer, so it is pre-malignant,
and it could become cancer via something called the adenoma carcinoma sequence.
Now, here's a picture of an adenomatous polyp.
You can see this raised protrusion of colonic mucosa.
Look at the normal glands here on the left bottom corner,
and then look at these glands which are much darker,
and this represents the adenoma or the neoplastic proliferation of glands.
Now, again, the key feature of these polyps is that they have the ability to undergo the adenoma carcinoma sequence,
and this becomes super high yield for exam, so let's sort of draw a spectrum here.
This is the surface of the colon, and in the normal colon, which I would draw here,
there is no risk of developing a polyp.
However, if the patient develops an APC gene mutation,
APC is called, APC is adenominus polyposis coli gene.
If the patient develops mutations in APC,
then what can happen is that creates a risk for the development of a polyp.
Now, of course, if you're at risk for development of a polyp,
in the next step, you can get a KRAS mutation,
and a KRAS mutation would eventually allow for the formation of that polyp,
and eventually, that polyp can become carcinoma,
and the way by which it can develop into carcinoma is that you can get P-firmary,
you can get P-53 mutations, and you also need increased cyclooxygenase expression.
These are two things that are important for development of carcinoma from an adenominus polyp.
Now, this sequence is super high yield for examination purposes,
and I'd like to highlight a couple points.
Number one, APC creates a risk for the development of polyps.
APC is a tumor suppressor gene, so you have to knock out both copies to develop that risk.
Now, normally, in patients in the age of 40, 50, 60, 70, as they develop a few polyps in their colon,
they knock out somatically both copies of APC.
So there will be somatic mutation of both copies of APC,
and when you knock out both copies of APC, that increases the risk to eventually develop a polyp.
It is also possible to get a germline mutation of APC so that you knock out one copy because you received a bad copy from a parent,
and that's called familial adenominus polyposis syndrome, and we'll talk about that in just a few minutes.
So this is high yield, and it's also important to note that this is on chromosome 5.
Those are all the high yields concerning APC.
Tumor suppressor gene, when it's knocked out, you get the risk of developing a polyp.
It can be knocked out creating a couple polyps in a normal patient, but in patients with familial adenominus polyposis,
the gene is knocked out from a germline mutation, which then allows for the formation of thousands of polyps,
as you're well aware of, which is a characteristic of familial adenominus polyposis.
Okay, KRAS is the next mutation, and this allows for the formation of the polyp.
And P53, super high yield, allows for the progression to carcinoma.
Now notice that you also need increased cyclooxygenase, and one very high yield association here,
shows up on exams often, is that aspirin protects against this sequence.
So that patients who take aspirin, they will decrease the level of cyclooxygenase production,
and therefore they will protect against the adenoma carcinoma sequence, and that's very high yield.
Now of course, because adenominus polyps are relatively common, and because they have the ability to become cancer,
we want to screen for those polyps, and we want to get rid of them before they actually can develop into cancer.
So the way by which we screen is colonoscopy, where we can go in and look for the polyps,
and by testing for fecal occult blood, because sometimes these polyps can bleed.
Again, the polyps are usually clinically silent, but they can bleed.
Now, what's the goal? The goal is to remove that adenomatous polyp before it progresses to carcinoma.
One of the best ways to screen for these polyps is colonoscopy,
and what they do in colonoscopy is they take out all the polyps.
Now usually a patient at the age of 50 or 60 might have one or two polyps,
they'll remove those polyps, and they'll examine them microscopically.
The reason you have to take out all the polyps is because when you do colonoscopy,
you can't tell the difference between a hyperplastic polyp and an adenomatous polyp.
The only thing you see is a polyp, and so you take a piece,
and under the microscopy, we'll be able to make that distinction.
So all the polyps are removed and examined microscopically.
Now, one of the important things that they'd like you to know for examination
is that if you have an adenoma, let's say that there's a colonoscopy,
and an adenoma is removed, the question you could ask is,
what was the risk of that particular adenoma to become cancer?
Now, it's out of the patient, so it wouldn't become cancer,
but what was the theoretical risk for that adenoma to become cancer?
And there are three key risk factors that tell you that there was an increased theoretical risk.
Number one, size greater than two centimeters.
If you have a polyp greater than two centimeters,
that would suggest an increased theoretical risk.
Also, if there's sessile growth, what does that mean?
When you look at polyps, polyps can kind of grow in two ways.
The first way, as I'm illustrating here,
is a pedunculated polyp where it grows off a stalk.
And the other way would be for the polyp to go flat along the wall.
So this pattern is called the sessile pattern,
and this pattern is called the pedunculated pattern.
And the sessile pattern theoretically has the more risk to develop carcinoma.
And then the final is the histology.
When you look at the histology of a polyp,
the polyp can have a bunch of these tubular spaces,
in which case it's called a tubular adenoma,
or the polyp can have a bunch of long villus-like projections coming from it,
in which case it's called a villus adenoma.
And so the villus histology is theoretically more worrisome
for the development of, for the potential development of carcinoma.
And there's that funny mnemonic that the villus histology is the villain in this particular discussion.
Now familial adenomatous polyposis is an autosomal dominant disorder
in which you knock out the APC gene.
If the APC gene gets knocked out,
then of course the patient now has a colonic mucosa that's at massive risk for development of polyps,
and over time you'll get progression to KRAS mutations,
and that'll result in the production of hundreds to thousands of adenomatous colonic polyps.
So this is the picture of familial adenomatous polyposis,
and you can see this whole surface of the colon is basically loaded with polyps.
Now in these patients you have to remove the colon and the rectum prophylactically,
and the reason is that once they get these polyps,
the possibility, the random possibility of one of these polyps progressing to get a P53 mutation
and increased cyclooxygenase, that is very likely.
And so basically because there's a very, very high risk of development of cancer,
the colon and the rectum are removed.
And in fact, if you don't remove the colon and the rectum,
the vast majority of these patients will actually develop carcinoma by the age of 40.
Now patients who have familial adenomatous polyposis
can sometimes have some associations with it,
and that would change the name of the disorder.
And so for example, if the patient has familial adenomatous polyposis
and also has fibromatosis and osteomas,
then that would be called Gardner syndrome.
Fibromatosis is a non-neoplastic proliferation of fibroblasts,
usually arises in the retroperitoneum,
and it's destructive, locally destructive.
And then an osteoma is a benign tumor of bone,
usually arises in the skull.
So the presence of FAP, familial adenomatous polyposis,
familial adenomatous polyposis with fibromatosis and osteomas,
that's called Gardner syndrome.
Turcotte syndrome is where you have FAP with CNS tumors,
in particular medulloblastoma and glial tumors.
Now there are some rare types of polyps that can also arise,
and I promised to discuss these at the very end of this section.
The first is a juvenile polyp.
This is a hemartoma.
Remember that a hemartoma is a tumor that's comprised of the tissue
that would normally be present, however it's disorganized.
It's a sporadic hemartoma, so therefore it's benign,
that arises in children less than the age of five.
Usually it presents as a solitary rectal polyp,
and that can prolapse and bleed.
So that's called a juvenile polyp.
Now it's possible to have multiple juvenile polyps,
due to some sort of polyposis syndrome.
In that particular case, you get a whole bunch of juvenile polyps
in the stomach and the colon,
and because you've got so many juvenile polyps,
it does increase the risk of progression to carcinoma.
So only with large number of juvenile polyps
would you worry about a risk for progression to carcinoma.
Poutierger syndrome is where you get hemartomatous polyps
throughout the GI tract,
but it's also associated with mucocutaneous hyperpigmentation
on the lips, the oral mucosa, and the genital skin.
This is an autosomal dominant disorder.
There's an increased risk in these patients for colorectal,
breast, and gynecologic malignancies.
And so that's Poutier-Jager syndrome.
That closes off our section on colon,
and the last section in the chapter is colorectal carcinoma.